Okay, this is it.
Let's get a look at the tool that we'll be using to create our awesome projects while learning to code.
If you haven't already done so, go to the website scratch.mit.edu.
This is where all the action is going to happen.
And because this is the first section of the course, I'm going to keep my happy, smiling face in the
corner of the screen because I want you to know that we are real humans on the other side of the computer,
teaching you not just some bot.
However, as we progress and get into this fun action parts where you will learn how to build some really
awesome games, I'll hide my face.
So we really want you to focus on the programming without distractions.
But don't worry because we are always here and ready to help you.
But with that, let's get going!
Firstly, let's take a moment to understand what scratch is.
Essentially, scratch is a programming language that has been specially designed for young coders and
people who just want to get started learning to code like you.
It basically takes the complex syntax and text from text based languages, and turns it into an easy
to understand code blocks that makes programming engaging, interactive, and fun.
You know how you can build all kinds of amazing things with Lego blocks, right?
You can create buildings, vehicles, and even entire worlds.
So just like Lego blocks, scratch provides you with colorful coding blocks that you can snap together
to build your very own digital creations like games, animations, interactive stories, and much more.
And just like you don't need to be an architect or an engineer to have fun with Lego, you don't need
any previous coding experience to start creating with scratch.
It is really designed to be easy to understand, so you can focus on being creative and learning the
logic of programming and how to think like a programmer, which is the most important skill.
And the best part is you can achieve all this without ever getting bogged down by complex coding syntax.
So it's an awesome way to get to know what programming is all about and start your coding adventure.
So first things first, open up the scratch website if you haven't done already, and I'm going to recommend
that you use Chrome as your browser as you continue as scratch.
Just works better with Chrome compared to other browsers.
So if this is your first time going onto scratch, your screen should look something like mine.
If you scroll down, you'll see a bunch of cool projects that people like you have been creating, which
we will explore later.
At the top here you will see we have different options.
The first one is to create a project which we'll be doing a lot of.
There is the explore tab and this is where you will find more fun games developed by people using scratch.
And this is where people will be able to find projects you create as well.
Moving over there is an ideas tab which has some fun ideas for projects for you to create in the future.
And finally, the about section is everything well about scratch?
Okay, with that all said, we can create our scratch account.
Now this is important as it will make sure we can save our project and not lose our progress.
So all you need to do here is click Join Scratch.
And as you can see, it asks you for a username and a password.
This can be anything you like, but do make sure it's not your real name.
As it says here we will just call it our name.
Click and then the password can be whatever you like.
Just make sure that you remember it.
After this it asks what country you live in.
So now you get to scroll through this massive list to find your country.
Well, I live in South Africa, so that's right near the bottom.
And then it'll ask your gender.
Finally, it'll ask for an email.
It is important to enter your email correctly, as this is where scratch will send a confirmation.
Once you receive the confirmation email, you can click the confirmation link and you're all done.
You're brand new scratch account is created and we're ready to get going.
So your turn.
Get your scratch account set up and I will see you in the next lesson as we explore the scratch interface.